<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: christianity, | Silly Muddle]]></title>
  <link href="http://sillymuddle.github.io/blog/categories/christianity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sillymuddle.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-08T04:29:05+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://sillymuddle.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Silly]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Atheist Antics: Background]]></title>
    <link href="http://sillymuddle.github.io/blog/2016/02/07/atheist-antics/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-07T22:44:15+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://sillymuddle.github.io/blog/2016/02/07/atheist-antics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An enjoyable part of being a Christian online are all the wonderful atheists who you meet, who love to try to convince us that if we would just give up our belief in God, that our pesky brain damage would disappear. The latest in a steady stream of atheist apologists to try their hand at deconverting me, is  <a href="http://damndad.com/another-response-to-sillymuddle/">Lucas</a>.</p>

<p>Lucas is from a group which claims what ordinary Christians really mean when we use the word <em>faith</em> is:</p>

<blockquote><p>Pretending to know things you don’t know</p></blockquote>

<p>So, by definition, all people of faith totally irrational! We, apparently, don&rsquo;t care about evidence, or reason. Ironically the atheists who claim this irrationally <a href="http://www.iscast.org/documents/Faith_survey_overview_with_references.pdf">ignore surveys</a> showing that 98.5% of Christians disagree with this definition.</p>

<p>Lucas and his group go around go around trying to convince us pretending mortals to be absurdly skeptical. The group is dominated by <em>extreme</em> skeptics - outspoken Christ-Mythers who, in contrast to virtually all credentialled historians, either Christian or atheist, deny that Jesus existed. Some even deny that Paul existed. But their skepticism is not just confined to topics of religion and history. The head of the group is a scientific anti-realist, denying that we can say electrons and electromagnetic fields exist in reality.</p>

<p>Lucas' group has a novel solution to deal with inconvenient facts. You might think that having Paul&rsquo;s writings (let alone the many contemporaries who wrote about him) prove he existed, or that the huge weight of experimental evidence means electrons exist, but no. They&rsquo;ll just tell you that you don&rsquo;t know what evidence is, and deny those pesky facts could ever be relevant.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/sillymuddle">@sillymuddle</a><br>Present the real evidence. &quot;a vault full of parchment in dead languages agrees with me&quot; is not a suffiscient explanation.</p>&mdash; Steve (@youngidealist) <a href="https://twitter.com/youngidealist/status/681277408276692992">December 28, 2015</a></blockquote>


<p> <script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The pattern is repeatedly the same. Instead of weighing things up carefully: Simply deny that those forms of evidence (or reasoning) are valid. The same tactic works if you want to deny science, deny history, or even deny God. Ignoring whole categories of evidence and reason does not lead to believing true beliefs, but instead to rejecting them.</p>

<p>There are real problems with the group using irrational saleman techniques (and agressive rhetoric if that fails)- but the biggest problem I have is this skeptical epistemology is obviously far from reasonable. When members of the group are denying such straightforward evidence, the problem is not the evidence. <em>The problem lies with how they evaluate it</em>. How this group does it is obviously broken.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading the background. Next post I&rsquo;ll discuss <a href="https://twitter.com/thedamndad/status/694406195445047296">Lucas' argument</a> that we can never have evidence for God.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
